okay A little bit of this a little bit
of that make sure that I rub the
eyebrows vigorously and voila 20 years
younger
wow I am younger I can't drive anymore I
can't drink I have a weird aversion to
my parents telling me what to do and I
suddenly dread math class okay that
ain't it that's not the type of exerc
exer I'm talking about we're talking
about real exercise with scientifically
shown benefits where researchers
randomly assigned middle-age around age
40 to 60 people to perform an endurance
training routine or a resistance
training routine over four months and
then assessed what happened to their
skin in fact they assessed other aspects
of their health and performance but I
assume you already know that exercise is
good for your health so we'll skip that
data
here we're looking at skin elasticity
the higher the bar the better the at and
RT are aerobic or endurance training and
resistance training the white bars are
before exercise and the darker stippled
bars are for the after as we can see and
confirm statistically due to the
asterisks both exercises improved skin
elasticity so we know that exercise as a
whole improves skin elasticity but the
promise of the video is the best not
that exercise generally improves skin as
interesting a revelation as that might
be so the researchers compared dermal
thickness that's the thickness of a
large section of the skin that sits
below the surface that you see dayto Day
called the epidermis if the dermis is
thicker the skin is usually more useful
and full looking at that data we can see
that dermal thickness relative to
aerobic exercise is improved with
resistance training so this suggests
that resistance training has an outsize
benefit at least based off the metrics
of this study on you know skin health
and youth however I should mention that
when strictly looking at the before and
after So within the resistance training
group only not compared against aerobic
there was no effect that still doesn't
mean that resistance training didn't
have an effect effect just that
depending on which comparison that you
focus on You could argue different
interpretations I think that the aerobic
versus resistance training data that we
just went over makes more sense though
okay but why like we know endurance is
excellent for blood flow and also great
for our health so isn't it a bit
surprising that lifting weights or body
weight resistance exercise or anything
of that style would lead to better skin
over endurance training I mean not to
say that resistance training is a slouch
but for skin well the researchers looked
into that too by quantifying the various
genes related to proteins in skin as you
can see in the VIN diagram in blue are
the aerobic exercise Express genes and
in red are the resistance training
exclusive genes and the middle is the
shared clearly both exercise types have
unique skin Gene Expressions but the
researchers Focus their attention on
this this one BGN this is the gene for
Bly B glycin other than sounding like
something out of Dune is an anchoring
protein for collagen fibers collagen
fibers aren't just spit out of the skin
cells called fiberblast they need to be
organized and anchored to give the
dermis that's the section of skin that
we're interested in structure so if we
look at the data we're looking at Bly
gene expression as we can see there's no
change in the aerobic condition but
there is an increase in resistance
training but is this consequential well
before we discuss that allow me to
mention that if you like this kind of
deep analysis of studies I have a
research review where I release weekly
videos articles and a monthly podcast
with a focus on applicable information
there's a bunch of perks that I won't
bore you with just uh check out the link
in the description it's called the
physic insiders yeah it's yeah it's the
it's the one down there right just tap
the description box yeah it's the link
at the top oh oh you okay you're not
going to do it okay cool cool cool oh
screw me then okay so is this really
consequential well possibly but keep a
few things in mind one we're measuring
gene expression and as I've been
reminded over and over during my PhD
gene expression doesn't always mean more
protein is produced now since we
actually saw improvements in skin
thickness it seems likely that there's
an effect here although the increase in
expression is a small 10% not exactly
Earth shattering still there's another
reason to care apparently there's an
inflammation marker that correlates with
byly as byly levels are higher ccl28
this inflammatory molecule is lower we
see that here the Bly gene expression is
on the vertical axis and the ccl28
levels are on the horizontal the line is
called a line of best fit and this is an
easy reference based on the data points
rather than scrambling our brain trying
to see a pattern as Bly expression is
greater this relates moderately with
lower ccl28 levels in fact the
researchers also indicate that
resistance training reduces ccl28 blood
levels so the actual protein the
researchers point out that they've done
cell experiments where they actually
apply ccl28 to cells and they observe a
reduction in byly expression directly
implicating ccl28 inflammation as a
regulator and suppressor of Bly a key
protein in skin health so let's put all
this together straight up I do think
some of the data in this study is weak
for more reasons than just the one or
two that I mentioned here I'm not saying
that it was poorly done just that I'd
want to see more evidence and stronger
evidence to really believe leave
everything here however we know one
thing and we are somewhat sure about
another coming back to the title of this
video considering some people are
probably Shell Shocked by the amount of
data shown instead of a health
influencer making up a bunch of BS
anyway back to the title number one
exercise plain old movia muscles
exercise will improve skin that we know
two the type of exercise that is
superior is still a bit up in the air
but leans in the direction of resistance
training the participants of the study
exercise twice a week by the way I
wouldn't worry about the specifics of
the routine it likely doesn't matter
much just stick to any basic
well-established routine I actually have
a free one available in my physionic
community also in the description box
under the link for the Insiders that you
ignored earlier so resistance train like
your skin depends on it Buffalo Bill
will be very po pleased